welcome back to 5-minute fizz today
we're talking about three huge nutrition
mistakes I see people make when they're
trying to change their diet lose weight
or improve their performance so number
one removing before adding now this is
what happens when people start new plans
they start coming up with a list of a
bunch of things they don't get to eat
anymore
and then often is their favorite foods
so this is a problem quite frankly
because it makes the diet now
restrictive and unfun so the inevitable
result is you're not gonna follow it
very well we will break down you'll have
huge cheat meals or other kinds of
problems so I suggest an alternative
approach which is a three-step system
now I've seen other people present
things like this and they're all
fantastic I give full credit to whoever
invented this if I knew but nonetheless
I think it's a very good approach to
first add quality food items and fix
deficiencies so if you happen to
understand that you have a specific
ailment or a low amount of zinc or iron
or something like that and you can add
that back into your diet you're gonna
automatically start feeling better if
you don't know those details and most of
us don't that's totally fine just start
adding quality foods into your diet
focus on getting more good in and you'll
probably take care of a lot of those
issues now the reason I like that is a
first step approach is it changes the
entire outlook on the diet to being
something that we're trying to improve
upon rather than something that we're
restricting or taking away the entire
outlook changes that way in addition if
you give people early wins what happens
is I can I start feeling better I'm
recovering better I'm sleeping better my
mood improves whatever metric is
important to you they're much more
likely to buy in and that's gonna foster
long term success over the plant so even
if the diet diet goal is something like
weight loss don't cut calories first if
you'll notice on the graphic that's
actually step 3
show them early success help them
understand what it feels like to
actually feel better I'm recovering
faster or I'm getting better sleep or
whatever it is that they're most
interested in help them feel better
first and then move on to step 2 which
is now we can start adding or removing
some of those bad foods some of those
problematic foods and we can do that
after us and the second stuff because
we've already built that buy-in they're
excited about it they feel good it's no
longer such a big deal to give something
away because they can tangibly
understand the difference between when I
eat good stuff versus when I don't have
that good stuff in my diet then third
you finally adjust the calories whether
you're trying to gain muscle mass
improve recovery that means you're
probably going to go up a little bit in
calories or if you're trying to lose fat
mass you'll of course restrict them a
little bit but that's step number three
feel good at first mistake number two is
they don't match their diet to the
lifestyle and personality now if you've
ever listened to my podcast this is a
great time to go do it the body of
knowledge is what it's called and we did
a fantastic episode chapter one point
six called abundant survival this is
available on iTunes over the body of
knowledge calm now where I describe the
way I approach people's diets based on
their personality types and I classify
people either as a baker or cook or a
chef so you can find more detail about
that system there but basically what I'm
getting at here is if you set yourself
up in a position to fail you're going to
we have to realize that life forces
almost always win even for professional
athletes so let's put ourselves in a
position to succeed this includes things
like some of you are real detailed
people and you want a diet plan that
tells you exactly what to eat how how
many almonds to pick exactly how many
ounces of water to drink what time to
eat them in and you so then you need a
diet like that or you need to purchase
one or get a coach or write yourself one
that is that level of detail but some of
you like myself that gives actually
anxiety because it's way too much
information so you need to take the
opposite approach which is to find a way
to get the things done you need to but
with just a few simple rules alright so
again you can check out that podcast on
the body of knowledge for more detail
about how to do that then our final
mistake here number three is missing the
90% to hit the ten and what I mean by
this is some really high percentage I'll
call it 90% of really most quality diets
are about the same they fight back and
forth between that last 10
to be honest folks again even with
professional athletes that 10% it almost
doesn't matter
so tackle the 90% first and then make
these small adjustments later I'm not
gonna go through this entire list I'll
leave this up to you but here what I
classify to be up about the 90% of good
quality advisor instructions that most
diets will give you I truly feel like if
you hit most of these five of the six
every day or 5 to 7 excuse me every day
or or at least most of them in most days
you'll probably be in a really good spot
and I think if we did this alone if half
of our country or half the world follow
the 90 percent rule I think we can
single-handedly and the obesity and
probably most of our health epidemics so
that's it thanks for following us stay
tuned for next time if you want more
information like this you can check out
my social media at dr. Andy galco.com or
my website andy galco.com thanks a lot
we'll see you next time